<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bride royall, or The spirituall marriage betweene Christ and his Church Deliuered by way of congratulation vpon the happy and hopefull marriage betweene the two incomparable princes, the Palsegraue, and the Ladie Elizabeth. In a sermon preached vpon the 14. day of Februarie last past, the day of that royall marriage triumphant solemnization. At Steeple Ashton in Wiltshire by G.W. Master of Arts, and pastor there.</title>
            <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854781</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854781</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20225</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20225)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1015:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bride royall, or The spirituall marriage betweene Christ and his Church Deliuered by way of congratulation vpon the happy and hopefull marriage betweene the two incomparable princes, the Palsegraue, and the Ladie Elizabeth. In a sermon preached vpon the 14. day of Februarie last past, the day of that royall marriage triumphant solemnization. At Steeple Ashton in Wiltshire by G.W. Master of Arts, and pastor there.</title>
                  <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 84 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for R. Mabbe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: George Webbe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth, --  Queen, consort of Frederick I, King of Bohemia, 1596-1662.</term>
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20225:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20225:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BRIDE ROYALL, OR The Spirituall Marriage betweene CHRIST and his CHVRCH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deliuered</hi> By way of congratulation vpon the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and hopefull marriage betweene the two imcomparable Princes, The PALSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GRAVE, <hi>and the Ladie</hi> ELIZABETH.</p>
            <p>IN <hi>A Sermon preached vpon the</hi> 14. <hi>day of</hi> FE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRVARIE laſt paſt, the day of that Royall Marriage triumphant <hi>ſolemnization.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At <hi>Steeple Aſhton</hi> in Wiltſhire by <hi>G. W.</hi> Maſter of <hi>Arts, and Paſtor there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> for <hi>R. Mabbe.</hi> 1613,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20225:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20225:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCES.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>THE MOST NOBLE</hi> AND ILLVSTRIOVS PRINCE, LORD <hi>FREDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RICKE THE V.</hi> COVNT PALATINE OF RHENE, ELECTOR OF THE SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRED EMPIRE, ARCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEWER, AND VICAR GENERAL IN THE VA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CANCIE OF THE EM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PIRE, DVKE OF BAVA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIA, KNIGHT OF THE MOST HONOVRABLE ORDER OF THE <hi>GARTER.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20225:3"/> AND <hi>TO THE MOST</hi> EXCELLENT AND <hi>ALL—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERTVOVS</hi> PRINCESSE, THE LADY ELIZABETH, ELDEST AND ONLY DAVGHTER OF THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE Prince, Our gratious Soueraigne, <hi>IAMES</hi> By the grace of GOD <hi>King of Great</hi> BRITAINE, FRANCE, <hi>and</hi> IRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>All</hi> Grace, and Glorie; Peace, and Pietie; Proſperitie, and Felicitie, <hi>be multiplied and continued, here, and euer.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>OVCHSAFE</hi> (Great <hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous PRINCES)</hi> amongst the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rare Pageants, and rich Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents
<pb facs="tcp:20225:3"/>from <hi>Court, Citie,</hi> and <hi>Vniuerſitie,</hi> exhibited to your Excellencies, as tokens of the common reioycing in your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Nuptials, To accept this poore Countrie preſent of a Punie Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine,
<note place="margin">To Artaxerxes.</note> who like the <hi>Perſian Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant,</hi> is deſirous to offer ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what (though it be but a <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of water)</hi> amongſt the reſt. In the memorable day of your Highneſſe happy eſpouſals, when all true-hearted Chriſtians, like <hi>Zerubbabels</hi> followers,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zechar.</hi> 4.7.</note> with ioyfull acclamations did crie <hi>Grace, Grace vnto it;</hi> I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with my ſelfe, like the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> of <hi>Samaria,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King</hi> 7.9.</note> that I ſhould not doe well to hold my peace, for it was a day of good tidings.</hi> Therefore to the glorie of God and honour of the
<pb facs="tcp:20225:4"/>day, I addreſſed my ſpeech vnto my wonted Audience, as, in my iudgment, was beſt befitting the preſent occaſions. What my Tongue did then aduenture to deliuer, my Pen ſhortly after was bold to ſcrible ouer, and now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought from the Pulpit into the Preſſe, it preſumeth to preſſe into the Court, and to ſeeke San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie vnder your Highneſſe Protection.</p>
            <p>Pardon (most excellent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) this my preſumptuous bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in aſpiring to offer this ſo raw a ſubiect to ſuch Royalleies. It hath nothing in it (with all humilitie I acknowledge it) wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of vulgar aſpect, much leſſe of gratious acceptance; My ſole Apologie is, that in the vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mine heart, out of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20225:4"/>of mine inward ioy, to the manifeſtation of my moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obſeruance towards your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Excellencies, I haue aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to caſt my poore mite into your abounding <hi>Treaſurie:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with mine eyes, and hearing with mine eares the triumphant acclamations, generall congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and religious ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the people, amongst whom I liue, at the admiration, and for the benediction of your Princely marriage, <hi>or euer I was aware,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.12.</note> my ſoule made mee like the Chariots of Amminadab.</hi> And albeit when I had thus ſet forth my ſelfe, I perceiued that I was vnmatchably preuented in the vnmatchably preuented in the ſame courſe, which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to runne, by a reuerend, learned, and religious <hi>Cuſhi,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20225:5"/>who had ſet forth before me,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Willets</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of <hi>Salomons</hi> mariage, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the ſame high and mightie Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. <hi>Virgil. Aeneid. lib.</hi> 2.</note> and by many degrees had <hi>ouer-run me,</hi> yet I was of <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpirit, deſirous (though like <hi>Aſcanius, non paſſibus aequis)</hi> to runne after. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit a wiſe and well-experienced <hi>Ioab,</hi> might haue ſaid vnto me, <hi>Wherefore wilt thou runne,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 21.22, 23.</note> my Sonne, ſeeing that thou haſt no tidings readie?</hi> yet (ſuch is the headlong raſhneſſe of youthfull diſpoſition) I ſetled my ſelfe vpon <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> reſolution: <hi>But howſoeuer, let mee run.</hi> Wherein, as I can hope for no greater acceptance of ſuch ſimple ſeruice, then what was ſpoken to <hi>Ahimaaz,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 30.</note> Turne a-ſide, ſtand by;</hi> yet I humbly craue of your gratious Excellencies, this fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable cenſure, that like <hi>Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maaz,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20225:5"/>I may be deemed <hi>a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning man;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27.</note> My will was good, though great my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The Prince of the Kings of the earth, out of the riches of his mercie multiply his graces vpon your Princely Perſons; That your Highneſſe (right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Prince) may be as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.4.5.</note> a Father of many Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> a Father of mighty Kings, as <hi>Iacob,</hi> your ſeede may be in many waters:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 24.7.</note> The eternall God multiply vpon you the zeale of <hi>Dauid;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.139. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 4.34.</note> The wiſdome of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon;</hi> the courage of <hi>Ioſhua;</hi> The honour of <hi>Ioſiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 1.6.</note> The ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Hezekiah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.25.</note> The ſtrength of <hi>Beniah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.27.</note> and the long life of <hi>Methuſelah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.20.</note> that you may ſo farre in all Princely and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall vertues ſurpaſſe all the
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.27.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:20225:6"/>former, both Electorall and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall <hi>Fredericks,</hi> as you haue exceeded them in the happy lot of your bleſſed marriage choiſe. And as for your Highneſſe (most religious, excellent, and admired Princeſſe) the King of heauen make your Royall perſon like <hi>Sarah</hi> a Mother of many Kings;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.16.</note> like <hi>Rebecka</hi> a Mother of thouſands of millions, whoſe ſeede may poſſeſſe the Gates of their enemies;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.60.</note> like <hi>Rahel</hi> and <hi>Leah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth.</hi> 4.11.</note> which two did build vp the houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> The God of Peace encreaſe more and more in your ſacred ſoule the deuotion of <hi>Hannah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.1. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.22.</note> the holineſſe of <hi>Hul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.33. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4.15.</note> the wiſedome of <hi>Abigail,</hi> the charitie of <hi>Heſter,</hi> the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimitie of <hi>Iudith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudith.</hi> 2. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.</note> and the dignitie of <hi>Deborah;</hi> yea the
<pb facs="tcp:20225:6"/>Lord double vpon your Grace, the long life, admired vertue, and admirable proſperity of that now triumphant Saint our late renowned Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whoſe ſweet name your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe beareth. The bleſsing of the moſt bleſſed <hi>GOD</hi> rest and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine with you both, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his most holy name, the comfort of our dread Soueraigne your Royall Father, the ſolace of our gratious Queene your happy Mother, to the reioycing of our peereleſſe Prince <hi>Charles</hi> your hopefull Brother, to the honor of <hi>Britannie,</hi> and ornament of <hi>Germanie,</hi> yea to the generall happineſſe of all thoſe that loue and feare the <hi>LORD IESVS,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20225:7"/>whoſe name be bleſſed now and for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Excellent Highneſſes humble Seruant</hi> In all dutie and ſeruice in the Lord, readie to be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>GEORGE WEBBE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20225:7"/>
            <head>THE BRIDE ROYALL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 45.13, 14, 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ. 13.</hi> The Kings Daughter is all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious within, Her cloathing is of wrought Gold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ. 14.</hi> Shee ſhall be brought vnto the King in rayment of needle worke: The Virgins her Companions that follow her, ſhall be brought vnto thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verſ. 15.</hi> With gladneſſe and reioycing ſhall they be brought, They ſhall enter into the Kings Palace.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Dayes common Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, becauſe of the happy Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Nuptialls ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more then common cauſe,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20225:8"/>I could not chooſe, but make di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion from our ordinarie and common Theame, and fit both Text and Speech vnto the Time. As therefore not long ſince, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of our publike loſſe, I called you to a publike mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; So now in this renewed occaſion of our generall gaine, I am to call you to a generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing. For as the vntimely deaths of hopefull Princes, are ominous preſages of enſuing miſeries, and therefore to bee condoled; So the hopefull mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of vertuous and religious Princes, are Auſpicious begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of future happineſſe, and therefore to bee congratulated. Wherefore let no man taxe it as a matter either ridiculous, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, for vs that liue here in the Countrie, to participate in any ſort with this daies triumph of the Court, ſeeing that not Court alone, but Countrie alſo,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20225:8"/>and (if I not much miſtake my ſelfe) whole Chriſtendome is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed in this dayes buſineſſe: yea, I doubt not, but in forraine countries, as wel as here in ours, the confederate Nations, and all true-hearted Chriſtians, whoſe hearts and minds are linked with the band of the ſame Religion together with vs, ſo many as heare of it, doe greatly ioy and reioyce in it. And ſhall not we, whom this ſo nearely (how near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we know not) doth concerne, reioyce herein, and celebrate this a ioyfull Sabboath vnto the Lord? Doubtleſſe <hi>this is the day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.23.</note> the happy day, <hi>which the Lord hath made,</hi> it is our dutie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce &amp; to be glad in it. Though our bodies be farre abſent from the pleaſtant ſpectacle of theſe ſolemnities, yet may our ſoules keepe a ſolemnitie of thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, though our hands can adde nothing to this daies triumph by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20225:9"/>our outward ſeruice, yet may our hearts weare inward Hymenaean Garlands of ſpirituall ioyes, and ſtrew the Bridall flowers of zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous praiers, for their good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</p>
            <p>My Text,
<note place="margin">The generall Argument of this Pſalme.</note> which to this end I haue made choiſe of, doth well befit this preſent purpoſe, and paralell this occaſion; for the whole Pſalme is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A Bridall Song, or marriage Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſung by the ſweet Singer of Iſrael, in the behalfe of a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage betweene a no meane or obſcure couple, but a Kings daughter and a King, betweene the greateſt Bridegroome, and the happieſt Bride. The Bride here in my Text, I confeſſe, farre greater then <hi>Great Britaines</hi> Daughter; The Bridegroome farre more glorious then any, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>German</hi> Prince or earthly Monarch. For the marriage here is ſpiritually to bee vnderſtood,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20225:9"/>betweene the Meſſias and the Church; Chriſt being the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, the Church the Bride; He the Spouſe, She the Spouſeſſe; He the Husband, Shee the Wife. So that albeit I may not wreſt this Scripture, or retort it from the myſticall marriage, at which it aimeth vnto the materiall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, at which I aime; yet, I hope, without prejudice to the Text, in the inter-view of the one, I may haue a collaterall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect at the other; eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the holy Ghoſt hath ſo nearly combined them both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. For here in this Pſalme is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended a two-fold mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; The one Literall, the other Myſticall; The one in the Letter, the other in the Senſe: The Literall Marriage is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Salomon,</hi> King <hi>Davids</hi> Sonne, and the Daughter of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of Aegypt: The Myſticall marriage is betweene
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20225:10"/>Chriſt Ieſus the eternall Sonne of the euer-liuing God, and the Church collected out of Iewes and Gentiles: The one is as the ſhaddow; the other is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: The one is the Type; the other the thing prefigured.</p>
            <p>The whole Pſalme doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of two parts:
<note place="margin">The Diuiſion of the Pſalme.</note> of a deſcription; Firſt, of the Bridegroome: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, of the Bride. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, in the twelue firſt verſes; the latter, from thence vnto the end of the Pſalme.</p>
            <p>The Bridgroome is deſcribed:
<note place="margin">The ſubdiuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the firſt part.</note> firſt, from his Perſon, <hi>v.</hi> 2. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, from his might and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5. Thirdly, from his wealth and dignitie, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7. Fourthly, from his Robes and Veſtments, <hi>v.</hi> 8. Fiftly, from his traine or retinue, <hi>v.</hi> 9.10. Sixtly, from his Fauourites and Homa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12.
<note place="margin">The diuiſion of the Text.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Bride (of whom at this preſent I intend only to ſpeake)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20225:10"/>is deſcribed: firſt, from her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, ſhe is <hi>The Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> Secondly, from her beautie, ſhee is <hi>all glorious within:</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from her Ornaments or Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall attire, <hi>Her cloathing is of wrought gold, her raiment of needle worke:</hi> Fourthly, from her traine or companie; <hi>The Virgins that be her Companions and follow after her, ſhall bee brought vnto thee:</hi> Fiftly, from her pompe and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-ſolemnitie, <hi>With ioy and gladneſſe ſhall they be brought, and ſhall enter into the Kings Palace:</hi> Sixtly, from the fruits of this marriage, and promiſe of poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; <hi>In ſtead of thy fathers thou ſhalt haue children, whome thou maieſt make Princes in all Lands:</hi> Seuenthly, from the memoriall of it and ſtabilitie; <hi>I will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy name from one Generation to an other, therefore ſhall the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple giue thanks vnto thee world without end.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20225:11"/>
            <p> The two laſt circumſtances are out of the compaſſe of my preſent text; the particular bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches whereof are ſo many, and the limited time ſo ſhort, that I ſhall be conſtrained to omit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy points of Doctrine, which from thence I might col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: and that which I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in handle, I ſhall but point at, becauſe I endeuour to be briefe. In the handling wherof, firſt and principally I will touch the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the words, <hi>Chriſts</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual marriage with the <hi>Church,</hi> and then deſcend to make ſome ſhadow or reſemblance of it in the Royall mariage, which is this day ſo hopefully, and, I hope, ſo happily celebrated.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Kings Daughter.</head>
               <p>THe firſt thing which this ſweet Singer of Iſrael doth chant forth in the commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Circ.</hi> 1. Who is heere meant by the Kings Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20225:11"/>of this Spirituall Bride, is her parentage, that ſhe is deſcended of the blood Royall, <hi>Filia Regis,</hi> a Kings Daughter. Alluding lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vnto <hi>Salomons</hi> Queene, which was the King of Egypts daughter, but vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically the Church of Chriſt, which is the King of Heauens Daughter. For, as <hi>Salomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was a liuely type of Chriſt, ſo the wife of <hi>Salomon</hi> was in this reſpect a reſemblance of the Church, who is the wife of Chriſt. As that Egyptian Ladie before her marriage with <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> was altogether Heatheniſh: ſo this Ladie before her Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all marriage with Chriſt, was altogether Helliſh. As her father was an Egyptian, ſo the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches naturall parents, Infidels: Thy father was an Amorite, thy mother an Hittite, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.3. As ſhe, before this marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, was brought vp in blindnes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20225:12"/>and ſuperſtition. So the Church, before Chriſt did ſpread ouer it the skirts of loue, was ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with errours and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Againe, as <hi>Salomons</hi> wife was a Kings Daughter, ſo the Spouſe of Chriſt is the King of Heauens Daughter. As ſhee by marriage with <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> was made a Queen: ſo the Church by marriage with Chriſt is made a Royall Bride. As ſhe after marriage became the mother of a King: ſo the Church after her Spirituall marriage with Chriſt, becommeth a mother of Kings and Princes, whom ſhee bringeth forth, and nurſeth vp to Chriſt. So that what once was ſpoken to the glory of <hi>Matild</hi> the Empreſſe, that ſhe was <hi>Regis filia, Sponſa, Nurus,</hi> a Kings Daughter, a Kings wife, and a Kings mother, may much more gloriouſly bee ſpoken of the Church, ſhe is <hi>Regis Filia, Sponſa, Nurus,</hi> the Daughter of the King
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20225:12"/>of Heauen, who begate her; the wife of the King of Glory, who redeemed her; the mother of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtian, Kings and Princes, borne of her and nouriſhed by her. The Church of Chriſt is this Kings Daughter.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> The which title may ſerue to ſhew forth vnto vs the excellent dignitie and glorious excellency of the Church of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">The Churches excellencie.</note> 
                  <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things are ſpoken of thee, thou Citie of God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the earthly Ieruſalem,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 87.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.3. We may well apply it to this heauenly Ieruſalem, <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things are ſpoken of thee, thou Church of Chriſt.</hi> It is called the <hi>Beautie of the earth, Pſal.</hi> 12 2.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.</note> The <hi>light of the world, Matth.</hi> 5.14.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.14.</note> The <hi>Standard of the Nations, Iſa.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.22.</note> 49.22. The <hi>golden Citie, Reuelat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.2.</note> 21.2. It is called the <hi>City of God, Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. The <hi>Houſe of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19.</note> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. The <hi>Temple of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. 1. <hi>Co.</hi> 3.16.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16. The <hi>Body of Christ,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20225:13"/>Rom.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.5.</note> 12.5. The <hi>Fulneſſe of Chriſt, Epheſ.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.23. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11:2. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.9.</note> 1.23. The <hi>Spouſe of Christ,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. The <hi>Lambes Bride, Reuel.</hi> 19.9. She is called <hi>A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man clothed with the Sunne,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reuel,</hi> 12.1.</note> Reu.</hi> 12.1. The <hi>Fairest amongst wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cani.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26.</note> Can.</hi> 1.8. Chriſts <hi>Sister, Cant.</hi> 4.10. The faithfuls <hi>Mother, Gal.</hi> 4.26. The Prince <hi>his Daughter, Cant.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant</hi> 7.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13.</note> 7.1. And heere in my text, <hi>The Kings Daughter.</hi> I omit the many and almoſt infinite ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes &amp; compariſons, by which this Church of Chriſt, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie therof, is deſcribed: ſhe is compared to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>allies, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.5.</note> and Cedar trees, Num.</hi> 24.5. <hi>To the Roſe of the field,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.2.</note> and the Lilly of the vallies.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.13.</note> To an Orchard of Pomegranats, a fountain of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.15.</note> and a well of ſpringing waters,</hi> in the Song of Songs. All which teſtimonies &amp; compariſons (with many more, which to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I might alledge) do plainly ſhew vnto vs, that amongſt all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20225:13"/>the Societies, amongſt all the daughters of the world, there is none ſo excellent, none ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, none ſo amiable, none ſo louely, none ſo beautifull, none ſo pretious, as is the Church of God. So that vnto her wee may apply that of <hi>Salomon, Prou.</hi> 31.29.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 31.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Many daughters haue done vertuouſly, but this ſurmounteth them all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> For whereas other States are but <hi>Filiae Terrae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">From the Churches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.9. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44.</note> Children of the Earth, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.9. <hi>Filij Belial,</hi> Sonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Filij irae,</hi> Children of wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. <hi>Filij Diaboli,</hi> Children of the Diuell, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44. The Church of Chriſt &amp; euery member ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is of an heauenly race, and of the blood Royall, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij lucis,</hi> Children of the light, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.36. <hi>Filij promiſsionis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.36. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8.</note> Children of the promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Filij regni,</hi> Children of the kingdome, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Filij
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20225:14"/>&amp; Filiae Rogis,</hi> Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the King of Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; as here in my text:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13.</note> 
                  <hi>God the Father</hi> doth vouchſafe to be called <hi>their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.</note> Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Christ,</hi> his onely Sonne by Nature, doth not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine to be called <hi>their brother, Hebr.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.11.</note> 2.11. The <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> is their inſpirer and preſeruer,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14. They are borne of God, and haue his ſeed remaining in them,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9.</note> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Reges nati, nati ad regnum,</hi> Kings by birth, borne to a kingdome.</p>
               <p>Againe,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> All other ſorts of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties amongſt the children of men,
<note place="margin">From the Churches pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge.</note> are but vaſſals and homa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers vnto the Church. Thus ſaith the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay.</hi> 55.4.</note> 
                  <hi>The labour of Egypt, the Merchandize of Aethiopia, and of the Sabeans, ſhal come vnto thee, and they ſhall be thine, they ſhall fall downe before thee, and ſay, Surely God is in thee, Iſay</hi> 45.4. And in another place,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings ſhall bee thy nurſing fathers, and Queenes ſhall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20225:14"/>be thy nurſing mothers, they ſhall worſhippe thee with their faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the earth, and licke vp the duſt of thy feete Iſay</hi> 49.23.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label>
                  <note place="margin">From her portion or dowrie. <hi>Gen.</hi> 43.34.</note> this Princely Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath a Princely portion aboue all other, as <hi>Beniamins meſſe was fiue times as much as his brethrens.</hi> So the Churches portion is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely beyond the portion of the worldlings.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> Her <hi>Portion</hi> is a <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Luke</hi> 12.32. Her <hi>Ioynture</hi> is <hi>an inheritance,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. Her <hi>Dowrie</hi> is <hi>an eternall waight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> 1. <hi>Peter</hi> 5.10. A Kingdome,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10.</note> 
                  <hi>which cannot be ſhaken, Hebr.</hi> 12.28.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.7.</note> An inheritance, <hi>which ſhall neuer faile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Tit.</hi> 3.7. A waight of glory, <hi>which is ineffable,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> 2.9. <hi>Eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, neither hath it entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that</hi> loue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Which excellencie of the Church, may adminiſter vnto vs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20225:15"/>many an excellent vſe.
<note place="margin">Of comfort to the faithfull in their medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> As firſt, matter of comfort vnſpeakeable to the Godly: for ſeeing the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and excellencie of the Church is ſo great and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, therfore they muſt needs be bleſſed and moſt happie, who are members of it;
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold what loue the Father hath giuen vnto vs, that we ſhould be called the ſonnes of God,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.1. <hi>God</hi> is become our <hi>Father,</hi> The <hi>Sonne</hi> is become our <hi>Redeemer,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is become our <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> are become our <hi>Attendants,</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are become our <hi>Euidences,</hi> the <hi>Sacraments</hi> are become our <hi>Seales,</hi> the <hi>Creatures</hi> are become our <hi>Seruants.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 3.21.22.23.</note> All things are ours, whether they bee things preſent, or things to come, all are ours, and wee Chriſts, and Christ Gods,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21.22.23. Let this then comfort thee (deare Chriſtian) againſt all ignominie, and wrong, by any limbe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20225:15"/>offered vnto thee. Doth any childe of <hi>Belial</hi> depiſe thee, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way reproach thee? Comfort thy ſelfe; thou art right deare and pretious in the ſight of God, and in the account of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</note> Thou art a Kings ſonne, or, a Kings daughter, thou art a darling of the King of heauen; they are but peaſants, ſlaues, villaines, vaſſals in regard of thee. Giue ſenſeleſſe dogs leaue to barke againſt the Moone? There is neuer a <hi>Baala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiſh</hi> curre amongſt them all,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.10.</note> but would wiſh that <hi>his latter end might be like thine:</hi> and that after this life ended, he might go with thee, though but as thy dogge, to heauen.
<note place="margin">Comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt feare of want.</note> Let this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thee againſt feare of want, and threate of foe. In time of dearth thou ſhalt haue enough: thou art the Kings childe. Hee that <hi>feedeth the fowles of the aire,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 6, 26.</note> and cloatheth the graſſe of the field:</hi> He wil much more prouide both
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20225:16"/>food and cloath for his owne childe.
<note place="margin">Of foes.</note> And why ſhouldeſt thou feare a mortall man, or the ſon of man, in whom there is no ſtrength? <hi>Feare not</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I am he that created thee, I haue redeemed thee, I haue called thee by thy name. Thou art mine; when thou paſſeſt thorow the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I will be with thee; when thou walkeſt thorow the fire, the flame ſhall not kindle vpon thee, Iſay</hi> 43.12. And what though Satan lay ſore ſiege at the caſtle of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed ſoule?
<note place="margin">Of Satan.</note>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Yet the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt thee:</hi> for thou art the daughter of the King of heauen:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12.7.8.</note> 
                  <hi>The great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> ſhall fight for thee: The <hi>Red Dragon</hi> nor any of his <hi>Bitterns</hi> ſhall neuer be able to ouercome thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> But let this ſtrike a terror and amazement into the hearts of all thoſe,
<note place="margin">Of terror to the Churches perſecutors.</note> who are perſecutours of this Princely daughter, whether
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20225:16"/>they perſecute her, or any mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her, whether with their <hi>tongue,</hi> as <hi>Shimei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7.</note> or with their <hi>geſture,</hi> as <hi>Iſmael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.19. <hi>Act.</hi> 12.1.</note> or with their <hi>hands</hi> as <hi>Herod,</hi> whether cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, as <hi>Iezabel,</hi> or openly,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.14. 3. <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.</note> as <hi>Pharoah,</hi> whether by themſelues, as <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> or by others, as the <hi>Scribes and Phariſies.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.3.</note> That which was ſpoken to railing <hi>Rhabſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kah</hi> out-brauing <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> may very well be applied vnto them, <hi>Whom haſt thou reproached and blaſphemed? Againſt whome haſt thou exalted thy voice, and lifted vp thine eyes on high? euen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy one of Iſrael, Iſay</hi> 37.23. Baſe wretch, knoweſt thou whom thou goeſt about to diſgrace, to wrong, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach? Surely one that is farre better then thy ſelfe, a Kings ſon or daughter; euen a child of the King of heauen. Will a King ſee his child wronged, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge it? Will a King put vp an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20225:17"/>indignitie offered vnto his royall blood, if he haue power and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to redreſſe it? But this our heauenly King is <hi>omni-ſcient,</hi> and therefore ſeeth: He is <hi>omnipotent,</hi> and therefore able to reuenge the wrongs and iniuries offered vnto any of his children: He hath ſaid, that <hi>Whoſoeuer toucheth any of theſe, toucheth the apple of his eye. Deut.</hi> 32.10. The wrongs done vnto them he reckoneth as done vnto <hi>himſelfe, Act.</hi> 9.4. The Lord will <hi>ſmite thorow thy loynes, O thou hater of his children, Deut.</hi> 33.11. It had beene better for thee that thou haddeſt beene ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer borne, <hi>Better that a Milſtone were hanged about thy necke, and that thou wert drowned in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the ſea, then that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt offend any of the King of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens little ones, Matth.</hi> 18.6.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> ſeeing the Church of Chriſt is ſo excellent and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<note place="margin">For direction.</note> let this ſerue for our directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20225:17"/>Firſt, that for our owne part we vſe all diligence to make it ſure to our ſoules, that wee are members of it.
<note place="margin">In our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> We ſee how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men are to be enfranchiſed into priuiledged places, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporations,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 22.28.</note> how they ſtriue for it, and rather then they will forgoe it, giue a great ſumme of money for it. How much more ſhould we endeuour to be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, whereby we are not only made <hi>free Denizens</hi> of heauens Kingdome,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.5.</note> but alſo ſonnes and heires, yea Kings and Prieſts in this kingdome, <hi>One day in Gods Court is better then a thouſand elſewhere: It is better to be adore-keeper in the houſe of God, then to dwell in the tabernacles of wickedneſſe, Pſal.</hi> 84.2.10.
<note place="margin">In our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> And let this not only make our ſelues willing me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Gods Church, but let it alſo incite vs to bring our ſonnes and daughters into the lap of this heauenly Kings
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 43.6. <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.21.22.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20225:18"/>daughter; to conſecrate our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with <hi>Hannah</hi> to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice;
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11.</note> and to prepare them to be <hi>Brides vnto the holy Lambe, Reuel.</hi> 19.7. Wee all, that are parents, doe deſire to preferre our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to good marriages, to linke them to honeſt families, and thinke it a great grace to vs and them, if they may bee matched into great houſes, or Noble bloods: But what is all the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, greatneſſe, wealth, or dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the world, to the dignity of the Church: What a glorie is this, to haue our children linked into the blood celeſtiall, to haue our ſonnes, <hi>Sonnes of Zion,</hi> our daughters, <hi>daughters of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> to haue them married to <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and to bee ſons and daughters to the King of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen?
<note place="margin">In our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full recordati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> And finally (that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this point) if <hi>Dauid,</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> had diſſemblingly profered vnto him his daughter <hi>Merab</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20225:18"/>bee his wife, as one aſtoniſhed, made anſwere, <hi>Who am I, and what is my life? Or what is my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe in Iſrael, that I ſhould be ſonne in law to a King,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.17.18. How much more iuſtly may euery Chriſtian ſoule, when as the eternall God doth, not by ſeeming ſhew alone, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, but really and royally per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the profer; not to be ſon in law alone, but to bee his very ſonne or daughter, by adoption: ſay with holy admiration and thankfull recordation; Who am I, or what is my fathers houſe? or what is there in me, that I ſhould be the ſonne, or the daughter of the King of heauen? We may wel ſay, with the penitent Prodigall, O heauenly Father, <hi>Wee haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt heauen and againſt thee, and are not worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thy ſons, make vs as one of thine hired ſeruants, Luk.</hi> 15.18.19. For vs, who are but <hi>duſt and aſhes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.27.</note> It
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20225:19"/>were a great priuiledge to be the ſeruants of his ſeruants, to be his vaſſals, his bond-men; to be but <hi>doore-keepers</hi> in the houſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.10.</note> were a great priuiledge and honorable ſeruice;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19.</note> but to bee <hi>fellow citizen with the Saints, and of the houſhold of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.15.</note> to bee not <hi>ſeruants,</hi> but <hi>ſonnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note> to be not only <hi>ſonnes,</hi> but <hi>heires,</hi> yea <hi>heires</hi> of God, yea <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low heires</hi> with Chriſt, What heart can ſufficiently conceiue of this ſo great a grace? What affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction can ſufficiently admire it? What tongue can one halfe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it? Thinke on it, and bee thankefull for it: thou being a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the Church, art a Kings child, Gods daughter, the Spouſe of Chriſt. And thus much brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Churches excellencie; proceed wee now to the ſecond circumſtance, which is the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Bewtie: <hi>The Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is all glorious within.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20225:19"/>
               <head>All glorious within.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Circ. </seg>2</label> THe ſecond <hi>Encomium</hi> here ſpoken to the commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this royall <hi>Bride,</hi> is <hi>her glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious beautie,</hi> wherein ſhee doth excell: ſhee is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all heauenly, all glorious, full of Beautie; For her <hi>beautie,</hi> ſhee is <hi>glorious,</hi> for the <hi>Quantitie</hi> of it, <hi>All glorious,</hi> For the <hi>Qualitie of it,</hi> Inwardly glorious, <hi>All glorious within.</hi> It would bee too prolixe a Treatiſe for mee to handle in order euery one of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and therefore I will contract the maine ſumme and principall ſcope of them all, into one ſhort doctrinall propoſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> The Church of God, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,
<note place="margin">The Churches beautie.</note> in this world not wholly free from ſome outward blemiſhes, yet inwardly is moſt glorious, and in the ſight of God, All glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. That the Church of God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20225:20"/>whiles it ſoiourneth here in theſe militarie Tents of this world,
<note place="margin">Not vvholly freed from out vvard black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> is not altogether free from out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward blemiſhes, may appeare by her owne confeſſion of her ſelfe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4.5. <hi>I am black, but come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (O yee daughters of Ieruſalem) as the Tents of Kedar, as the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of</hi> Salomon; <hi>Looke not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, becauſe I am black, becauſe the Sunne hath looked vpon me,
<note place="margin">The reaſon of it.</note> my Mothers children were angrie with me,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> &amp;c.</hi> where is declared the reaſon how and whence it is that in this glorious church there appeareth ſometimes this ſwart hue of outward blackneſſe: Firſt, it lyeth ſubiect to the ſcorching Sunne of affliction, <hi>The Vallie of Bacha,</hi> is their Campe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84 6. The <hi>Croſſe</hi> is their <hi>Standert, Luk.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Perſequutions</hi> their <hi>colours, Ioh.</hi> 15.20. <hi>Trialls</hi> their <hi>comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Pſal.</hi> 34.19. <hi>Sorrowes</hi> their <hi>foode, Pſal.</hi> 88.15. <hi>Teares</hi> their <hi>drinke,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Pſal.</hi> 119. Secondly, It is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20225:20"/>enuironed with falſe bretheren within, and infeſtuous enemies without; The ſtate of it is like the <hi>Arke floating vpon the waters, Gen.</hi> 7.17. <hi>Like a Lilly amongst the Thornes, Cant.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Like a Lambe amongst Lyons, Pſal.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Shee</hi> is compared to a <hi>corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> wherein are ſome <hi>Tares</hi> as well as <hi>Wheat, Mat.</hi> 13.25. To a <hi>Net</hi> where are ſome <hi>badde fiſh</hi> as well as good, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47. To a <hi>threſhing floore,</hi> wherein is <hi>chaf</hi> as well as <hi>corne, Mat.</hi> 3.12. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>band of Men,</hi> in which there are ſome white-liuered, as well as valiant Souldiers, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.7. To a <hi>great houſe</hi> wherein are <hi>veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of diſhonour,</hi> as well as <hi>veſſels of honour,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. In regard whereof, Sometimes this Kingly Daughter outwardly appeareth ſo <hi>black,</hi> that there can bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned <hi>no forme of beautie in it, Iſay</hi> 53.2. Sometimes ſo <hi>barren</hi> that there appeareth little fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20225:21"/>in it, <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.27. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo <hi>deſolate,</hi> that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to <hi>hide her ſelfe in the wilderneſſe, Reuel.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p>Wherein then appeareth the Churches glorie?
<note place="margin">Yet invvardly glorious. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Shee is</hi> (ſaith my Text) <hi>glorious within:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly glorious; Her glorie is more internall then externall: There is a twofold ſtate of the Church, <hi>Outward and inward:</hi> The <hi>outward</hi> eſtate of the Church ſtandeth in viſible aſſemblies, in the publike Miniſterie of the Word and Sacraments, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Diſcipline and Gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And in this reſpect (as I haue before touched) ſhee may ſometimes ſeeme by reaſon of the iniquitie of the times, to bee ouer-clouded with blackneſſe; The <hi>inward</hi> eſtate of the Church ſtands in the true knowledge of God in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Wherein this invvard glorie doth conſiſt.</note> in comfort touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remiſſion of ſinnes and life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting, in the gifts and graces
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20225:21"/>of the Spirit, and in Gods prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And in this reſpect ſhee is right glorious, yea a moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bride.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> For what glorie is it to haue a painted out-ſide,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and a moſt deformed in-ſide? like a <hi>Tombe</hi> gilded outward, but <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in full of dead Mens bones, Mat.</hi> 23.27.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It is the inward vertue which God requireth; <hi>My Sonne</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>giue mee thine heart, Pro.</hi> 23.26. <hi>Thou deſirest truth in the inward parts, and in the hidden part thou ſhalt make me to know wiſedome, Pſal.</hi> 51,6.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is this inward glorie which the Lord reſpecteth: the inward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament of <hi>a meeke and quiet Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the ſight of God</hi> is of great price, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4. This <hi>inward</hi> beautie of the Church what tongue of man can ſufficiently expreſſe?
<note place="margin">Seuen degree of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches invvard glorie.</note> For a glimpſe hereof (for that is all that I can deliuer of it) we may note in it theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen degrees: firſt, The <hi>Poſſeſsion</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20225:22"/>of Gods word,
<note place="margin">Barthol. Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus, in hunc locum.</note> and the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the true God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.7.8.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>What Nation is ſo great, that hath God ſo night vnto them, as the Lord our God is vnto vs? What Nation is ſo great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, that hath Statutes ſo righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as all this Law? Pſal.</hi> 147.19.20. <hi>He hath ſhewed his word vnto</hi> Iacob, <hi>his Statutes and his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vnto</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Hee hath not dealt ſo with any Nation:</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The <hi>confidence</hi> in prayer, and <hi>aſſurance</hi> of the hearing of her prayers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>We haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the Spirit of adoption, where by we crie</hi> Abba, <hi>Father; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer wee aske wee receiue of him,</hi> 1.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.22. Thirdly, <hi>Perpetuall preſeruation</hi> in the midſt of all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>The gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it, Iſay</hi> 43.2. <hi>When thou paſſeſt through the waters I will bee with thee, &amp; when thou walkeſt through the fire, the fire ſhall not hurt thee:</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20225:22"/>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> To it belongeth the <hi>Conenant and the promiſe, Rom.</hi> 9.4. <hi>They haue a most ſure word of the Prophets.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. Fiftly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> It is adorned with the gracious gifts of the Spirit, as <hi>Loue, ioy, peace, long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekeneſſe, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, Gal.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The world is not worthy of them, Heb.</hi> 11.38. Sixtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> It is ſecure and voide of ſeare; <hi>Wee will not feare, though the earth be moued, and though the mountaines bee carried into the middeſt of the Sea, Pſal.</hi> 46.2. They haue the <hi>peace of conſcience which paſſeth all vnderſtanding, Phil.</hi> 4.7.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Seuenthly, It hath the inheritance of life euerlaſting, &amp; the promiſe of endleſſe glorie. They are <hi>Heires according to the hope of eternall life, Tit.</hi> 3.7. To them is reſerued <hi>an eternal waight of glorie,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. This is the Churches inward glorie.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe of this inward
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20225:23"/>glorie,
<note place="margin">Therefore in Gods ſight it is <hi>All glorious.</hi>
                  </note> notwithſtanding the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward defects and blemiſhes, it is eſteemed wholly glorious: <hi>All glorious,</hi> ſaith my Text. So ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth our ſpirituall <hi>Salomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in this his glorious Brides co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendatiue deſcription, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4 <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.2.3.4.5.6.7. <hi>Behold thou art faire my Loue, behold thou art faire; Thou haſt doues eyes within thy lookes; Thy haire is as a flock of Goats that appeare from Gilead; Thy teeth are like a flock of ſheepe; Thy lips are like a threed of ſcarlet; Thy ſpeech is comely, &amp;c.</hi> at laſt hee concludeth in the ſeuenth Verſe, <hi>Tota es formoſa, amica mea, Thou art all faire, my Loue, there is no ſpot in thee?</hi> No ſpot? How can that bee? ſeeing the Church her ſelfe doth acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her owne <hi>blackneſſe, Cant.</hi> 1.8. and her owne <hi>drowſineſſe, Cant.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> 5.2. <hi>Shee is all glorious:</hi> firſt, in regard of Chriſts imputation;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  <hi>Hee gaue himſelfe for it, that hee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20225:23"/>might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the Word, that he might preſent it to himſelfe a glorious Church, not hauing ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy, and without blemiſh, Eph.</hi> 5.26.27. Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In reſpect of Gods acceptation; <hi>Since thou waſt pretious in my ſight thou haſt beene honorable, and I haue loued thee, Iſay</hi> 43.4.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, In regard of the future glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of it; It ſhall bee <hi>full of glorie, Reuel.</hi> 21.23.</p>
               <p>Wee haue ſeene this point of the Churches beautie briefly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed;
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt the Browniſts.</note> Let vs now ſee it for our farther vſe applied. And here, firſt, ſeeing the Church, and, ſo by conſequence a particular Church, is a glorious Church, if it haue inward ſoundneſſe, albeit it be not wholly freed from out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward blemiſhes; then confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded be all <hi>Kathariſts, Donatists, Browniſts, Separatists,</hi> or by what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20225:24"/>name elſe ſoeuer they be called, who peremptorily take vppon themſelues to condemne thoſe Churches, which wholly fit not their humours, or haue ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion of outward blackneſſe, to be <hi>baſe Churches, falſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, no Churches.</hi> Blind Buſſards they are, not able to diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſubſtance and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, betweene Doctrine and Manners, betweene the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hue, and the inward beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. contra Creſ. Gram. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 38.</note> 
                  <hi>It followeth not</hi> (ſaith learned <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt ſome furious Spirits of that Schiſmaticall ſect) <hi>becauſe of many euils, therefore no true Church, if that blackneſſe marre not the foundation, it may be a glorious Church in Gods eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The <hi>Church of Corinth</hi> was a true Church, notwithſtanding their <hi>manifold diſorders,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. The <hi>Church of Epheſus</hi> was a true Church notwithſtanding her <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinings, Reuel.</hi> 2.4. The <hi>Church
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20225:24"/>of Pergamus</hi> was a true Church, notwithſtanding ſhe was ſeated euen in Sathans circuit, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred with the deuilliſh Sect of <hi>Baalamites</hi> and <hi>Nicholaitans, Reuel.</hi> 2.13.14.15. So was <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> notwithſtanding her <hi>Ieſabeliſing, Reuel.</hi> 2.20. So was <hi>Sardis,</hi> notwithſtanding her <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure deadneſſe, Reuel.</hi> 3.1. So was <hi>Laodicea,</hi> notwithſtanding her <hi>luke-warmneſſe, pouertie</hi> &amp; <hi>naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Reuel.</hi> 3.16.17. Hath not the brighteſt day his cloude? the fineſt Lawne his brack? the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt gold his droſſe? And is there or was there euer any Church in the world, that might not bee tainted with ſome blemiſh, that may not bee touched with ſome imperfection? Denie as well they may that there is no Sunne in the firmament, becauſe it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ouer-clowded, and no Soule within that Bodie which outwardly is deformed.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20225:25"/>
               <p> Againe,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Is the Churches beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie more within,
<note place="margin">Againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</note> then it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out? Is it her greateſt glorie to be all glorious within? why then do ſeduced and ſeducing Soules who are bewitched with the Circean dregs of the Babyloniſh Roman Strumpet,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17.4.</note> ſo much glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the outward pompe and glorie of their Baſtard Church? Their glorious Copes, Shrines, Miters, Croſſes, Banners; Their garriſh Proceſſions, Pardons, Beads, Candles, Chriſmes; Their Eare-pleaſing Organs, Bells, Quiers, Deſcants; Their Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſening Exorciſmes, Vnctions, Cenſing, Sprinckling, Miracles; Their Linſie-woolſie coat of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, Ieſuits, Friars, Monks, Nunnes, Capuchins, Anchorites; Their Comicall and Mimick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and the whole rabble of their Pontificall Solemnities, wherin the glorie of their church doth wholly conſiſt; what are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20225:25"/>they (being ſeparated from this inward glorie) but at the beſt a painted out-ſide of an ill-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured Strumpet? meere toyes to mock an Ape, ſubiects of ſcorn rather then of admiration? <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous within;</hi> This hath no inward glorie, therefore no Daughter of the King, but a beggerly Baſtard brat, begotten of Antichriſt on the ragged Whoore of Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme. What one inward note of glorious beautie can there bee ſeene in the Popiſh Church? The word of God out of it is barred; His Sacraments by it are adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; His Diſcipline from it exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; His Saints in it perſequuted; and for all the outward pompe and glorie of it, It is vgly inward, being become the <hi>habitation of Deuils,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reuel.</hi> 18.2.</note> and the hold of euerie foule Spirit, and a Cage of euerie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane and hatefull Bird.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But leauing theſe,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> let vs come
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20225:26"/>nearer vnto our ſelues,
<note place="margin">Againſt car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> and from the conſideration of particular Churches, let vs deſcend to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons, that profeſſe themſelues members of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church; Seeing this Kings Daughter, the Church of Chriſt, is inwardly glorious: with what face can they claim their intereſt here, or profeſſe themſelues members of the Church, who neither haue, nor care to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inward or outward glorie? Atheiſts, Epicures, Libertines, Worldlings, and the whole rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of prophane perſons, bewray themſelues to bee none of this Societie, to be none of this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Churches members; for were they ſo, they would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to be more glorious. Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Worldling, where is thy glorie, whiles thine affections are altogither earthly, and thou both ſauoureſt, and ſeekeſt the things of this world, which are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20225:26"/>ſo baſe and tranſitorie? Volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Epicure, where is thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, when thou walloweſt in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pleaſures, and worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, like the dirtie Swine, which lie tumbling in the mire? Is it a ſeemly thing for a Princes Sonne, or a Kings Daughter, to ſpend their time and ſtrength in ſeruile and ſlauiſh actions, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Hogs, &amp; playing the Skull, and running on errands at the command of euerie one that will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand them? how much more vncomely and abiectly baſe is it for thee, who profeſſeſt thy ſelfe a member of the Church, a child of the King of heauen, to ſpend thy pretious time in ſeeking after contemptible vanities, and to be at the ſeruice and beck of Sinne and Sathan, for the baſe hire of worldly trifles, neuer thinking of ſpiritual preferments, &amp; glorious priuiledges, but ſetting all to ſale for the preſent fruition of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie toies.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20225:27"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> Wherefore (beloued) let vs, ſo many of vs as doe profeſſe our ſelues to be of this heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly bloud Royall,
<note place="margin">For our dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.9.</note> if we would approue our ſelues of the generation of God, if his ſons and children in Chriſt Ieſus, if heires of God, &amp; coheirs vvith Chriſt, if Brides vnto the Lamb; let vs euermore ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this inward glorie; <hi>Let vs be holy,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leuit.</hi> 20.6.</note> becauſe he our God is holy.</hi> Let vs practiſe holineſſe, vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vvhich no man ſhal ſee God.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</note> Let vs endeuor to be ſincere and vvithout offence,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.10.</note> till the day of Chriſt. Let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider our ſelues, that vve are <hi>a choſen generation, a Royall Prieſthood, an holy Nation, a peculiar People, that wee ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes of him who hath called vs</hi> out of darkeneſſe <hi>into his meruailous light.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>5</label> And let this be our comfort in this our glorious practiſe,
<note place="margin">For conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that albeit we are far from perfection in this lifes Sanctification, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20225:27"/>things all ſinning, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.7. Hauing the <hi>Fleſh</hi> luſting againſt the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> againſt the <hi>Fleſh, Gal.</hi> 5.17. Though here we cannot wholly bee free from ſpot and blot; yet ſo long as we delight in the Law of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>inward man, Rom.</hi> 7.12. and ſtriue forward towards the marke for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.14. Wee haue a gracious Father, who wil ſpare vs as a man ſpareth his owne Sonne that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him, <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Wee haue an Advocate with the Father Ieſus Chriſt the iust, who is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation</hi> for our ſinnes, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.1.2. In him we are preſented to God without ſpot or wrinckle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. and for his ſake, in Gods ſight wee are <hi>All gloricus,</hi> as it is here in my Text: <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glorious within.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:20225:28"/>
               <head>Her cloathing is of wrought gold, ſhee ſhall bee brought vnto the King in rayment of needle worke.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Circ. </seg>3</label> HItherto we haue ſeene this heauenly Bride in her out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward excellencie,
<note place="margin">The ſenſe of the words.</note> and in her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward beautie: now wee are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take view of her in her Royall Ornaments and Bridall attire. Her apparell, for the ground-worke, is <hi>Gold,</hi> for the frame of it, it is <hi>Wrought-gold;</hi> for the curiouſneſſe of it, it is <hi>Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of needle-worke.</hi> By Gold wee are heere to vnderſtand the Grace of God: by Rayment of needle-worke, the gifts of his holy Spirit. The former for the excellencie thereof, tearmed <hi>Wrought-gold;</hi> the latter, for the varietie thereof, called a <hi>Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of needle-worke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> Not to inſtance by way of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20225:28"/>diſcourſe vpon each of theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; in generall,
<note place="margin">The Churches Warderobe.</note> beere wee may behold this heauenly Bride, the Churches wedding garment. Euery Chriſtian ſoule being a member of the Church, and ſo maried vnto Chriſt Ieſus, is rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adorned with moſt glorious Royall Robes, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.10.11.12. They are ſaid to be clad with <hi>broydered-worke,</hi> with <hi>Badgers skinnes, fine linnen and ſilke, to bee decked with ornaments, bracelets, and golden chaines,</hi> to haue iewels in their foreheads, and earings in their eares, and <hi>beautifull crownes vpon their heads, Reuel.</hi> 3.12. They are ſaid to be clothed with <hi>White garments, Reuel.</hi> 6.9. with <hi>white roabes, Reuel.</hi> 12.1. to be clothed with the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and to haue the <hi>Moone</hi> vnder their feete, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>head</hi> to haue a crowne of <hi>twelue Stars, Reuel.</hi> 21.2. They are ſaid to bee <hi>prepared as a Bride adorned for her husband,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalme</hi> 45.13.</note> and here
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20225:29"/>in my text, <hi>Her clothing is of wrought-gold, her rayment of nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle-worke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we may take a more liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notice of theſe Royall wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Roabes: let vs take a briefe view: firſt, of the matter of them: ſecondly, of the parts of them: thirdly, of the faſhion of them: fourthly, of the fitnes of them.</p>
               <p>For the firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">The matter of this wedding garment.</note> as concerning the matter of this garment, of what ſtuffe it is; the Scripture telleth vs, that it is Chriſt himſelfe, with his imputed righteouſnes: <hi>They put on the Lord Ieſus, Rom.</hi> 13.14. <hi>They haue put on Christ, Galath.</hi> 3.27. <hi>He hath clothed me with the garments of ſaluation; He hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered mee with the robe of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, as a Bridegroome decketh himſelfe with ornaments, and as a Bride adorneth her ſelfe with iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Iſay</hi> 61.10. This is called the <hi>Wedding garment,</hi> without which no man can feaſt with the Lord,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20225:29"/>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.10. It is called the <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God,</hi> becauſe without it, no man is able to <hi>withſtand the wiles of the diuell, Epheſ.</hi> 6.11. It is called the <hi>armour of light, Rom.</hi> 13.12. becauſe it is the beautie and glory of them that weare it: it is called the <hi>righteouſneſſe of Saints, Reuel.</hi> 19.8. That is the matter of this wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Now for the parts of it (which is the ſecond circumſtance) the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth vnfold them all, and lay them open vnto vs,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">The parts of this wedding garment.</note> 
                  <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.1.2. <hi>Put on therfore, as the elect of God, holy and beloued, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of mercie, kindneſſe, humblenes of minde, meekneſſe, long-ſuffering, forgiueneſſe, charitie.</hi> Heere wee ſee the wedding roabes brought forth and ſorted: <hi>Bowels of mercy</hi> for our mindes cloathing, and <hi>kindneſſe,</hi> for our ſpeeches orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and amiable conuerſing, <hi>Humilitie</hi> for our outward carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20225:30"/>and our goings; <hi>Meekenes</hi> for our affections in our paſſions: <hi>Long-ſuffering</hi> for a cloake to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer wrongs: <hi>Forgiuing,</hi> as a badge of inward patience, and <hi>Charitie</hi> as the bond or combination of all other vertues. Theſe be the parts of this wedding garment, which that wee may apply them to the ſeuerall parts, for which they ſerue, The Scripture calleth in other tearmes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 6.11.</note> 
                  <hi>White robes</hi> of innocencie for their inward gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Pure holineſſe</hi> for their vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per garment:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> their breaſt-plate: the <hi>Goſpell of peace</hi> the ſhooe tyer:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 29.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Verity</hi> the girdle: <hi>Iuſtice</hi> their crowne: <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe with all his graces and merits,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14.</note> their <hi>tunica talaris,</hi> their cloake or gowne, wholly coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them.</p>
               <p>Theſe Royall robes,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">The faſhion of the wedding garment.</note> for their faſhion (which is the next point to be conſidered) are in compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; neuer out of faſhion, meete
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20225:30"/>for all ſeaſons, fit for all perſons; It is like <hi>Elias</hi> mantle which diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the waters, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 2.8. So this will diuide our ſinnes, and the puniſhments. It is like the garments of the Iſraelites in the wildernes, which did not weare out, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.5. So this apparell of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt doth laſt for euer, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are neuer worne out; It is like vnto <hi>Iacobs</hi> garments, as the ſmell of a fielde which the Lord hath bleſſed, <hi>Gene.</hi> 27.27. It is like vnto Chriſt himſelfe, yea the very Image and <hi>Idea</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.10. in whom alone God is pleaſed <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p>Therefore this Garment muſt needes bee fit (which is the laſt thing I obſerue in it.)
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <note place="margin">The fitneſſe of this wedding Garment.</note> It is not too ſhort, like the curtailed Coates of <hi>Dauids</hi> Embaſſadors, which couered onely their vpper parts, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.4. nor too long, like <hi>Sauls</hi> Armour which tired
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20225:31"/>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> when he ſhould fight with it, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.29. but it is wholly ſutable, like <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Coate which his father made him, <hi>Gene.</hi> 37.3. As therefore <hi>Mordecai</hi> ſhined in the Kings robes before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Heſt</hi> 6.11. So, and more glorious are the faithfull in the fight of God; being cloathed in the robes of Chriſt: As <hi>Chriſts</hi> face at the time of his transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration did ſhine like the Sunne, and his Cloathes were white as the light, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.2. So the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full being transfigured to this Image of Chriſt, <hi>Shallſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament and as the ſtarres for euermore. Dan.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his Royaltie was not ſo glorious, nor <hi>the Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the field,</hi> which were more glorious then <hi>Salomon,</hi> when he was moſt glorious, as is this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Bride cloathed with Chriſt and his righteouſneſſe, which is farre more precious then all the worlds riches.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:20225:31"/>
               <p> Seeing then that the Church of GOD and euery particular member of the ſame,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label>
                  <note place="margin">Examination.</note> is arraied with ſuch glorious robes: Let this ſerue, Firſt, to ſtirre vs vp to a diligent ſearch within our ſelues, whether wee haue on vs theſe wedding Cloathes or no? Without this wedding garment wee can haue no countenance from the Lord, nay there is not onely an indignation againſt vs, <hi>Friend how cameſt thou hither not hauing on a wedding garment?</hi> But alſo a condemnation, <hi>Binde him hand and foote, take him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, caſt him into vtter darkneſſe, Mat.</hi> 22.12. It will be therefore our wiſedome to ſearch and trie our Soules, whether they bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with theſe holy garments. And becauſe by nature we are all of a Laodicean temper,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.17.</note> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues, that wee are richly clad, when we are naked; therefore wee are the more to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20225:32"/>marke the faſhion of it, that we faſhion not our ſelues according to the faſhion of this world, <hi>For the faſhion of this world paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31. But followe this heauenly faſhion, and get this Bridall garment: If we haue found this garment, let it not lie by vs, but weare it, not a part of it, but the whole, not to put it off againe, as wee doe our ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Cloathes, but as a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all habite to be worne of vs.</p>
               <p>Againe,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> ſeeing this Bridal gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſo needfull and ſo helpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<note place="margin">For our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> Let this make vs more and more in loue with it, and carefull for to get it: Which for to get, wee muſt firſt ſeeke it where it may be had: <hi>I counſaile thee to buy of me</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Reue.</hi> 3.18) <hi>white raiments that thou maieſt be cloathed, and that the ſhame of thy nakednes do not appeare.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when we haue found it, <hi>Wee muſt ſell all that wee haue and buy
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20225:32"/>it, Mat.</hi> 13.46. Wee muſt doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our owne filthy and ragged cloaths, <hi>The conuerſation in times, the olde man which is corrupt through the deceiueable luſts, Ephe.</hi> 4.22. <hi>For our owne garments will defile vs, Iob.</hi> 9.3. and chaunge them for theſe robes which will ſo richly cloath vs. Thirdly, when we haue put it on, we muſt weare it cleanely, and comely from ſoyling and renting, that ſuch a garment bee not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from vs, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.39.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> ſeeing this Bride of Chriſt hath for her chiefeſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">For our pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne in our Attire.</note> the golden graces of Gods holy ſpirit wrought in a garment for her, by the needle-worke of the Preaching of the word; Let this bee a patterne as for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward attire, ſo for our outward habit: It is not the outward gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous attire, or the wearing of Gold,
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3.4.</note> or the putting off appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh.)
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20225:33"/>But the hidden man of the heart, the ornament of a meeke &amp; quiet Spirit, which maketh glorious, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. Would we then be gloriouſly attired? Let vs follow that good and graue Counſell of <hi>Tertullian,
<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de cultu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aem.</note> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtite vos ſeric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, biſsino ſanctitatis, purpura pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicitiae, Taliter pigmentatae deum habebitis amatorem,</hi> Cloath your ſelues (ſaith he) with the <hi>Silke</hi> of pietie, and the <hi>Satten</hi> of ſanctitie, and the <hi>Purple</hi> of modeſtie, thus being attired, the eternall God will bee your louer. And thus much of the Churches glorious ornaments and Bridall attire. <hi>Her clothing is of wrought Gold, her raiment of needle-worke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Virgins her companions that follow her, ſhall bee brought vnto thee.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Circumſt. </seg>4</label> FRom the conſideration of the excellencie, beautie and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20225:33"/>of the Bride,
<note place="margin">The litterall ſenſe of the words.</note> wee are now to proceede to the order and companie of the Bridefolke, to view the traine and companie of the Bride; which here after the maner of Bridals and Marriage ſolemnities, is thus deſcribed; <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins her companions that follow her, ſhall bee brought vnto thee;</hi> The companie are here <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,</hi> The reaſon, becauſe they are her <hi>Companions,</hi> The order, <hi>They follow her,</hi> The end, <hi>To bee brought vnto thee;</hi> They are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins,</hi> there is their <hi>qualitie;</hi> They are <hi>Companions;</hi> There is their <hi>dignitie;</hi> They <hi>follow her,</hi> that is their <hi>duetie;</hi> They are <hi>brought in with her,</hi> there is their <hi>feliaitie.</hi> By <hi>The Virgins,</hi> wee muſt here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all the faithfull, who by reaſon of their Virgine ſoules, are <hi>preſented chaſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins vnto Chriſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. The title of <hi>Companions</hi> noteth the mutuall fellowſhip and ſocietie which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20225:34"/>euery particular member of the Church hath with the whole, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. The order of <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after her,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 2.47.</note> implieth the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them vnto the Church, who are ordained to ſaluation. <hi>The bringing of them with her,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the meanes of the Churches increaſe &amp; diſcipline, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18.</p>
               <p>I ſhould be too tedious to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt vpon each of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <note place="margin">The Churches Companie.</note> And therefore I will drawe the doctrinall ſumme of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this ſhort compaſſe. Euerie one which would bee brought vnto Chriſt, muſt become a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine member, companion, and follower of the Church. When the daughters of the Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of the Meſſias,
<note place="margin">Saluation onely in the Church.</note> 
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Tell me O thou whom my Soule lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, where thou feedeſt, where thou makeſt to reſt at none?</hi> It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued this anſwere, <hi>verſe</hi> 8. <hi>If thou know not, O thou faireſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt women, goe thy way foorth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20225:34"/>by the footeſteps of the flocke, and feede thy Kids beſides the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards tents, Iſay</hi> 45.14. It is ſaid, that the faithfull ſhall bee the Churches, <hi>They ſhall bee thine, They ſhall come after thee,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Surely God is in thee and there is none elſe,</hi> Act. 2.47. <hi>The Lord ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Church from day to day, ſuch as ſhould be ſaued;</hi> So then there is no ſaluation out of the Church, But as all thoſe which were not in the Arke, periſhed in the generall deluge, <hi>Gene.</hi> 7.23. So all that are out of this Arke of Chriſt, which is his Church, ſhall be ſure to periſh eternally: <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out are Dogs, Enchanters, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and Adulterers, Reue.</hi> 22.15.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> And the reaſon heereof is plaine; For without Chriſt there is <hi>no ſaluation, Act.</hi> 4.12. But out of the Church there is no <hi>Chriſt</hi> nor <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.12. and therefore no ſaluation;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine foorth of the Militant
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20225:35"/>Church there are no meanes of ſaluation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. and therefore no ſaluation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery one which would bee brought to Chriſt, muſt ioyne himſelfe to ſome particular Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Neither is it ſufficient to bee corporally ioyned to the viſible Church,
<note place="margin">The members of the Church muſt be pure Virgins.</note> but we muſt be Virgine members of it, if truely wee doe belong vnto it: where by Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie I doe not vnderſtand that externall Virginitie of ſingle life, which the Papiſts ſo highly mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and enioyne;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rhem. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.32.</note> but that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Virginitie which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, <hi>Reue.</hi> 14.4. namely, <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and puritie of the ſoule.</hi> The members of the Church are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an <hi>holy nation,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. It is called the <hi>Companie of the ſpirit of iust men, Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Euery man that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelfe euen as he is pure.</hi> And good reaſon is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20225:35"/>there of this:
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> For <hi>what fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe? Or what communion hath light with darkneſſe,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14.</note> or what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord hath Chriſt with</hi> Belial?
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, euery man ſhould bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the qualitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Church whereof he doeth profeſſe himſelfe a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; now the Church is ſaid to be <hi>without ſpot or wrinkle, Ephe.</hi> 5.27. therefore euery one profeſſing himſelf a member of the Church, muſt endeauor to be ſincere and blameleſſe in the Church.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The wiſe Virgins that were inuited to the weding of the Lambe, tooke Oyle in their veſſels with their Lampes, and attended the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromes comming, but they are fooliſh Virgins, and ſhall not be admitted to the Bride-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who haue no oyle in their Lampes, that is, no holyneſſe in their liues, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, theſe pure Virgines,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20225:36"/>who are this royal Brides gueſts,
<note place="margin">They muſt promote and proture the good of the Church.</note> as they are companions of the Church, and as they are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into her ſociety, ſo they muſt follow her, and to the vtmoſt of their power ſeeke to promote and procure the good of her. <hi>Pray for the peace of Iernſalem,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſalme</hi> 122.6.</note> let them proſper that loue thee: peace be within thy Walles, and proſperitie within thy Pallaces,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 7.8.9.</note> for my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and companions ſake, I will now ſay, peace bee within thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God I will ſeeke to doe thee good, Pſal.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> 122. Where the Pſalmiſt ſetteth downe a threefold rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why euery member of the Church ſhould doe ſeruice to the Church,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and ſeeke the good of it; Firſt, in regard of their owne proſperitie, in the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of it, <hi>They ſhall proſper that loue thee.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in regard of others, who are their fellowe members in it, <hi>For my brethren
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20225:36"/>&amp; my neighbors ſake I wil now ſay, peace be within thee.</hi> Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the houſe of God, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeeke to doe thee good.</hi> Thus in briefe we haue ſeene this point of Doctrine proued, that none can bee brought to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but by Chriſt; none can bee brought to Chriſt, but in the Church; none are in the Church, but ſuch as endeauour to haue pure Virgins ſoules; none can haue this, but they muſt doe their beſt ſeruice for the Churches good.</p>
               <p>The vſe of this Doctrine may ſerue,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label>
                  <note place="margin">For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of thoſe who are out of the Church.</note> Firſt to diſcouer the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate of thoſe which either yet are not brought within the Pale of the Church, as <hi>Infidels, Turkes, and Ethnickes,</hi> or who wilfully leape ouer this Pale, and ſeparate themſelues from the Church, as <hi>Papiſtes, Familiſtes, Browniſts, and Anabaptiſts;</hi> The
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20225:37"/>
                  <hi>Papiſt</hi> of Pride, the <hi>Familiſt</hi> of Hypocriſie, the <hi>Browniſt</hi> of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie, haue ſingled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the Churches com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17.</note> as <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> did. If they ſeparate themſelues as ſtones from the building, and as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from the body, what hope is there of them? what a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doome is that, which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> doth giue concerning them? <hi>They went out from vs, they were not of vs, for if they had been of vs, they would haue remained with vs,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> this may ſerue for the terror of thoſe,
<note place="margin">Againſt the prophaneliues of thoſe who liue in the Church.</note> who liuing in the Church, and profeſſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues members of the Church, doe by their prophane and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly courſe of liuing, bewray themſelues not to belong vnto the Church. <hi>To the wicked</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>what hast thou to doe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my ſtatutes, or that thou ſhouldeſt take my Couenant in thy
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20225:37"/>mouth? ſeeing thou hatest instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and caſteſt my words behind thee, Pſal.</hi> 50.16.17. <hi>Will ye ſteale, murther, and commit adulterie, and ſweare falſely, and then come and ſtand before mee, and ſay wee are deliuered, notwithstanding all theſe abominations? Ier.</hi> 7.9.10. Gods houſe will not be a denne for theeues; the members of the Church muſt liue by faith: <hi>If any draw backe, my ſoule ſhall haue no pleaſure in him, Hebr.</hi> 10.38. The Brides followers muſt exhibite themſelues <hi>Chast Virgins vnto Christ,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. They muſt approue themſelues, as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins redeemed from amongst men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt fruits to God and to the Lambe, Reuel.</hi> 14.5. Otherwiſe they ſhall bee reiected like thoſe fooliſh Virgins, with a <hi>Non nout vos, Verily I ſay vnto you, I know you not, Matth.</hi> 25.12. <hi>Without holines no man ſhall ſee God, Heb.</hi> 12.14. And into the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20225:38"/>ſhall enter <hi>no vncleane thing,</hi> as it is, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.27.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Let this then prouoke vs all, more and more to ſanctitie and newneſſe of life,
<note place="margin">For our dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to all holy duties.</note> that wee may walke worthie of that calling whereunto we are called; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer things are honeſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.8.</note> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer things are iuſt, whatſoeuer thinges are true, whatſoeuer thinges are pure, whatſoeuer things are louely, whatſoeuer things are of a good report; if there be any vertue, if any praiſe, let vs thinke vpon theſe things and doe them. Let vs all ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the good of the Church with all our power, and bring ſuch as belong vnto vs into the boſome of the Church, that they and wee may haue fellowſhippe with God, and one with another: ſo ſhall wee haue a ioyfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the kingdome of grace, and an happy entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of glory; which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20225:38"/>is the laſt circumſtance to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>With gladneſſe and reioycing ſhall they be brought, they ſhall enter into the Kings Palace.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Circ. </seg>4</label> WE haue ſeene the Bride &amp; her glory,
<note place="margin">The literall ſenſe of the words.</note> the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſts and their dutie. Now in the laſt place wee are to behold the marriage pompe and ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. THEY [the Bride and her companions, the Church and her members] <hi>ſhal be brought</hi> [by the preaching of the word, and the working of the holy Spirit] <hi>with ioy and gladnes</hi> [with inward ioy and peace of conſcience, with outward comforts and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements.] <hi>They ſhall enter</hi> [here by the kingdome of grace] <hi>into the Kings Palace</hi> [the kingdome of euerlaſting glory.]</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:20225:39"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> Behold we here in a word the glorious manner and Maieſtie of the Churches marriage.
<note place="margin">The manner and Maieſtie of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches mariage.</note> The Churches marriage with Chriſt her Lord, is to the ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her heart be gunne heere in this life, but perfected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummated to her endleſſe glory in the life to come. Here in this life it is begunne;
<note place="margin">Heere in this life.</note> for ſo, <hi>Iſay</hi> 54.5. <hi>He that made thee i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thine huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the Lord of Hoaſts is his name, and thy Redeemer the Holy one of Iſrael:</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4.5. <hi>Thou ſhalt be called Hephzi-bah (or my delight is in her) &amp; thy land Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah (or married) for the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in thee, and thy land ſhall be married, as the Bridegroome reioyceth ouer the Bride, ſo ſhall thy God reioyce ouer thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The mariage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker.</note> The Author of this marriage or the marriage maker, is God the Father, who ioyneth his Sonne in marriage with the Church by his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: <hi>I will marrie thee vnto me for
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20225:39"/>euer, yea I will marry thee vnto me in righteouſneſſe, in indgement, in mercie, and in compaſsion, Hoſea</hi> 2.19.
<note place="margin">The meanes.</note> The inſtruments or meanes whereby God maketh vp this marriage here, are his Prophets, Apoſtles, and faithfull Miniſters, whom hee ſendeth to perſwade &amp; effect it: to eſpouſe it,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.15.</note> to bring it in, as here in my text, The fruit or benefit of it is ioy and gladnes to the Church:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. The ioy and comfort of it.</note> 
                  <hi>The King hath brought me into his chambers, wee will reioyce and be glad in thee, wee will remember thy loue more then wine: ioy and gladneſſe ſhal be found therein, thankeſiuing, and the voice of melodie: Iſay</hi> 51.3.</p>
               <p>But the conſummation of this heauenly marriage ſhall be in the world to come,
<note place="margin">In the life to come.</note> when this Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Bride ſhall <hi>receiue the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for her, Mat.</hi> 25.34. and ſee her bridgroome <hi>face to face,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. and <hi>enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his glorie, Mat.</hi> 25.21. and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20225:40"/>
                  <hi>raigne with him for euer, Reuel.</hi> 22.5. who can expreſſe the ioy and gladnes which then the Church ſhall haue, when it ſhall bee brought into her Bridegroomes preſence, and enter into this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Palace?
<note place="margin">The Palace.</note> It is paſt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Geometrie</hi> to meaſure it, paſt the numbers of <hi>Arithmetick</hi> to tell it, paſt the skill of <hi>Logick</hi> to define it, paſt the eloquence of <hi>Rhetorick</hi> to expreſſe it;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Renel.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22</note> Had I the tongue of Men and Angels, I could not vtter the one halfe of it. The <hi>Palace</hi> prouided for this marriage is the <hi>Heauen of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens,</hi> which for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is a <hi>glorious Citie,</hi> whoſe <hi>Gates</hi> are of <hi>Pearle,</hi> and <hi>Streets</hi> of gold, <hi>and walls of pretious ſtones. Reuel.</hi> 21. and for the <hi>ſituation thereof,</hi> is ſaid to bee beſet with <hi>a Riuer,</hi> the <hi>water whereof is Chryſtall, and the bankes ſet about with the Tree of life,
<note place="margin">The Temple.</note> Reuel.</hi> 22. The <hi>Temple</hi> for this marriage, <hi>The Lord God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20225:40"/>the glorie of God doth il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten it, and the Lambe is the light of it, Reuel.</hi> 21.21.23.
<note place="margin">The Brides Chamber.</note> The <hi>Bride-chamber the new Ieruſalem,</hi> a Seate of maieſtie, an Houſe of eternitie, a Palace of Royaltie, a Paradiſe of pleaſures.
<note place="margin">The Gueſts.</note> The <hi>Bride gueſts,</hi> Patriarks, Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors, and the Spirits of Men made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. Many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and the Weſt, and ſit downe with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.11. <hi>The cheare,</hi> Bread of life, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.51.
<note place="margin">The Cheare.</note> Wine of gladneſſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.18. Angels foode, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.25. Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, peace, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. Fulneſſe of ioy, &amp; eternall pleaſures, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11. The <hi>Attendants,</hi> Angels,
<note place="margin">The Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants.</note> Archangels, Principalities, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, Powers, Thrones, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. Cherubins and Seraphins, <hi>Iſay</hi> 6.2.
<note place="margin">The Muſick.</note> The <hi>Muſicke</hi> Hale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20225:41"/>
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.1. New Song, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 5.9. Songs that no man can learne, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.3. ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the voice of thunder, as the voice of many waters, and as harpers harping on their harps <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.2.
<note place="margin">The Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</note> Laſtly, the <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance</hi> of it, not for a day, or a weeke, or a moneth, or a yeare, not like <hi>Ahaſhueroths</hi> feaſt for an hundred and foureſcore dayes, <hi>Heſt.</hi> 1.4. But for <hi>a thouſand yeares, Reuel.</hi> 20.6. Yea for <hi>euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, Reuel</hi> 22.5. Thus this Bride of Brides being married to the King of Kings, in the Heauen of Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſhall time beyond time, with ioy paſſing al ioy, enioy the preſence of the Holy of Holies, keepe the Sabboth of Sabboths, and heare the Song of Songs.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed then and thrice bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> who may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this Nuptial banquet.
<note place="margin">To ſhew the pleſſed eſtate of the faithful.</note> The holy Choſt himſelfe hath ſealed vp the truth of this in his indeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20225:41"/>writ; <hi>Bleſſed are they which are called to the marriage Supper of the Lambe, Reuel.</hi> 19.9. <hi>O they be bleſſed that dwell in Gods houſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) they will be ſtill prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him, Pſal.</hi> 84.4. <hi>The Lord God is a Sunne and ſhield vnto them. The Lord will giue grace and glorie, and no good thing will he with-hold from them, Pſ.</hi> 84.11.</p>
               <p>VVhy then ſhould any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſoule goe mourning all the day long?
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label>
                  <note place="margin">For the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the faithfull.</note> and why ſhould the ſeruice of God ſeeme any way tedious? or any affliction grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous? <hi>The Lord is a plentifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder of them that ſeeke him, Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>One day in his Courts is better then a thouſand elſwhere, Pſal.</hi> 84.10. The ſufferings of this preſent time, are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee compared with the glorie which ſhall be reuealed in vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. Let it therefore be meate and drinke vnto vs to doe our Fathers will, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.34. Let
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20225:42"/>the Lords Precepts be the verie ioy of our heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.110. And let vs be glad, and reioyce, and giue honour to him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the Heauens, for the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Lambe, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.7.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> let vs trimme euery one of vs our owne Soules,
<note place="margin">For our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> and make our ſelues readie as a Bride, for this our heauenly Bridegroome; <hi>Let vs caſt off the old man which is corrupt according to the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full luſts, and put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, Eph.</hi> 4.23.24. Let vs put on the cleane white linnen of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 19.8. And the bright ſhining Robes of holineſſe, <hi>Exo.</hi> 39.30. Let vs waſh our handes in innocencie, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6. And ſhooe our fecte with veritie, <hi>Eph.</hi> 16. Let vs haue Faith in our hearts, and good workes in our hands: So ſhall we, like wiſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins &amp; the Brides Companions,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:20225:42"/>bee admitted with her into the chamber of Preſence; for ſo <hi>the Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come, and let him that heareth ſay Come, and let him that is a thirſt come, and whoſoeuer will, let him take of the water of life freely, Reuel.</hi> 22.17.</p>
               <p>I haue thus farre kept touch with my Text,
<note place="margin">Application of this heauenly marriage to the preſent roy all mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</note> and walked in the direct path thereof, I muſt now make a little digreſſion from the maine and principall ſcope ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to a collaterall application of it vnto this daies royall mariage, which gaue me occaſion to make principall choiſe of the Text. We haue ſeene the Text in the ſenſe of it; Now behold it in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it: We haue ſeen in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, now behold it in reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance: The Churches marriage with Chriſt her Lord is reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled (as wee haue heard) to the marriage of a Kings Daughter with a King. <hi>Ecce Symbolum,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the ſhadow of it in this
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20225:43"/>dayes Royall Bridall.</p>
               <p>I could trace my Text heere (though I confeſſe, from the Text) from point to point; and for our Bride, if wee goe no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the letter, I might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for the better: For was <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> Bride <hi>Filia Regis,</hi> the Daughter of a King? So is this daies gratious Bride, <hi>Filia Regis,</hi> a Kings Daughter; not the Daughter of a ſuperſtitious <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> or deſcended of an <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian King;</hi> but the Daughter of a religious and a learned Chriſtian King, a Defender of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith; one who hath been the glory of Schooles, and vniter of Kingdomes: <hi>Tanti Regis talis fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> of ſo great a King ſo gratious a daughter, yea the eldeſt daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yea the onely daughter, is this daies Bride.</p>
               <p>This our Kings Daughter is all glorious within, and not within onely, but wholly admirable:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20225:43"/>The God of Nature hath in her bodie made her a mirrour of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Beautie, and in her ſoule a patterne of Graces pietie: So that albeit in her outward ſhape to the ſight of men ſhe be excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glorious, yet inwardly to the ſight of her God, ſhe is moſt glorious: ſo gratiouſly all holy graces in her being ſo compact together, that it drawes the eies &amp; harts of al men to admiration, to ſee ſo much pietie in ſuch comely beautie, ſo great humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in ſuch a Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Neither doe her glorious Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall robes, be they neuer ſo glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering with wrought gold, or curiouſly embroydered by the art of man (as no doubt this day, for the ſolemnitie of it, and the honour of her eſtate, it is moſt glorious) ſo much adorne her, as the more then golden graces of Gods holy Spirit in her.</p>
               <p>The Virgins (companions ſhe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20225:44"/>hath none, being the only Iewel of this Northerne Ile, and the <hi>Non-parel</hi> of the reformed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world) the Virgin-daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that haue ſeene her, haue bleſſed her; forren Queenes and their Princely daughters that haue heard of her, haue praiſed her; the eare that hath heard her hath admired her, and the eye that hath ſeene her, hath giuen witneſſe vnto her.</p>
               <p>And therefore, no doubt, with ioy and gladnes both Court and Citie, Pallace and Country, doth this day triumph in her, pray for her, and ſay of her, Bleſſed be he that made her, happy is hee that begate her, renowned is ſhe that bare her, but moſt happy, renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and rich is he that hath her.</p>
               <p>How much are we, the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of this whole Ile, bound vnto our good God, that hath lent vs ſuch a Princeſſe, &amp; in her hath renued &amp; reuiued the name
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20225:44"/>and nature of our late deceaſed, euer to bee remembred, happie Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> a name in this Land euermore to bee beloued: for as much, as that now thrice vnder that name it hath beene bleſſed. The firſt of that name, to this Land ſo happy, being the great Grand-mother to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our preſent <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> happy in her marriage, and by her marriage, firſt vniting the two Houſes of Lancaſter and York, whoſe diſſentions did an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy this Kingdome with bloody ciuill warres, and then by the fruit of her marriage, vniting theſe two Kingdomes England and Scotland, which before were at continuall warres. The ſecond of that ſweete and happy name (whoſe remembrance is like that of <hi>Ioſias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 49.</note> like the perfume made by the art of the Apothecarie) ſweete as hony in all mens mouthes, and as muſick at a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20225:45"/>of wine) happy in her not marrying, for being a Virgin-Queene (whom no King or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of this world was worthy of) ſhee prepared her ſelfe a Spouſe for Chriſt, and hauing found the walles of this Realme of braſſe, turned it into marble, finding Religion in the ſands, ſhe did ſet it on the rocke: finding this a Land ouerwhelmed with ignorance and ſuperſtition, ſhee reſtored true Religion, and left it throughly ſeaſoned with the Goſpell: our ſelues, our children, and their childrens children, when they heare her name, ſhall call her Bleſſed. Our preſent <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth,</hi> this dayes Royall Bride, is of no leſſe happy hopes: her Loue vnto her Name-ſakes me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, her imitation of her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, her hatred of Popery and Superſtition, her zeale to Gods glory, and ſincere profeſſion of the Goſpell, her religious educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20225:45"/>from her infancie; Her reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent attention at the hearing of the word; Her reſpect vnto the Miniſters of the Goſpell; Her faith; Her zeale; Her charitie is admirable, and to euery Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an heart moſt comfortable.</p>
               <p>It was the deſire and often wiſh of this Gracious Princeſſe (if report of ſome of her neereſt obſeruants may bee credited) that in her Marriage match, ſhee might be linked to a Prince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the ſame Religion in which ſhee her ſelfe had beene inſtructed. Good Princeſſe (the God of Heauen be bleſſed for it) ſhee hath her wiſh: No ſonne of Antichriſt; No vaſſal to the Pope hath the firſt fruites of her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage bedde; No ſuperſtitious Maſſe doth defile the celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her Nuptials, or obſcure the glorie of her Marriage, but ſhee is matched with a Prince, in Religion, in education, in yeeres,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20225:46"/>in vertues fit, and fit for none, but for her ſelfe. Had ſhee, good Princeſſe, bin linked in Mariage with one of a different Religion, what an vnequall yoke had that beene? How derogatorie from Gods glorie? How preiudicious to our State? How dangerous to her perſon? How hurtfull to her Soule?</p>
               <p>But bleſſed be God, who hath prouided better things for vs, for Her, for his Churches good. Herein our Gracious Soueraigne hath manifeſted vnto the World the ſinceritie of his heart, and the ſoundneſſe of his profeſſion, in that no outward dignitie, ſtate or glorie, could cauſe him to match his Child with a contrarie Religion. Doubtleſſe the finger of God hath beene here, This match is of his eſpeciall chuſing; And indeede (did we well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it) what greater, what more glorious match, could wee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20225:46"/>wiſh for, or deſire, for our great Maſters onely Daughter? Theſe Kings and mightie Monarches, who haue ſubmitted their Crownes vnto the iuriſdiction of the Pope of Rome, are but vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals vnto the Pope, not abſolute Princes. This our <hi>Germaine</hi> Bridegroome is a free Prince, his ſtate is in ſubiection vnto none; Deſcended of moſt Noble and religious Progenitors, euen from that Houſe, which firſt of all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſet it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope,
<note place="margin">Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of the Church.</note> in defence of the Goſpell, and brought in the name of Proteſtaniſme; Himſelfe of that name, which to the Popes hath beene alwayes terrible, and of that carriage,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fridenrych,</hi> in the Germaine tongue, is as much as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> ſo <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>us Sprung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> in <hi>Iob Ho.</hi> 1</note> that in the eyes of all that feare the Lord, hath made him truely venerable: An other <hi>Salomon,</hi> for ſo doeth his Name in his Countrey language ſignifie: A young <hi>Ioſias,</hi> who hath ſet his heart to feare the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20225:47"/>LORD. Wherein, euen in his Name wee may ſee Gods great mercie towards vs; For whereas it pleaſed God of late (becauſe wee were vnworthy of him) to take away from vs our hopefull Prince HENRY FREDERICK, our Soueraignes Eldeſt Sonne (whoſe memoriall is, and euer ſhall be bleſſed) our loſſe (which was vnſpeakable) is heerein ſo much the leſſe, in that wee haue not wholly loſt him: for though HENRY bee gone, yet FRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERICK is left behinde. O happie day, bleſſed Marriage, happie Bridegroome, glorious Bride! This day is a day of good tydings, who can hold his peace? It is the day which the Lord hath made, we haue great cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and to bee glad in it; This day is Peace ratified, Religion eſtabliſhed, the Church beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>wealth ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the hearts of good Subiects
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20225:47"/>cheared, the friendſhip of confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Nations confirmed, <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie</hi> and <hi>Germanie</hi> combined. O Pray for the Peace and Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritie of this happie Bridall, Let them proſper which wiſh well vnto it; Let them bee confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that maligne it; Let them periſh that enuie it.</p>
               <p>And thou, O great <hi>Iehouah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A concluſion with a Prayer.</note> God Almightie, King of Heauen and Earth, who for the comfort of mankind haſt ordained Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and made it Honourable, and at this day more then Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, in the Royall Marriage of theſe two great and hopefull Princes; Bleſſe this thine owne ordinance, to thine owne glory, and their comfort: Thou thrice glorious and euer bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Almightie Father, Eternall Sonne, Inſpiring Holy Ghoſt, vouchſafe thy preſence at this their Marriage-meeting; Let thine holy Angels pitch their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20225:48"/>Tents about them, and let thy mightie hand graciouſly defend them from the malice of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and from the miſchiefe of the aduerſarie, and from all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that may beplotted againſt them. Knit thou their hearts and minds together with true Loue, with the bond of the Spirit, in the feare of thy name; Marrie them to thy ſelfe in righteouſneſſe, in iudgement, in louing kindneſſe, in mercies and faithfulneſſe; Let the Angels ſing happineſſe, and the Heauens drop downe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe vpon this their Mariage: Sanctifie their Marriage bed, and in thy good time make them fruitfull in procreation of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that they may haue many Sons and Daughters whom they may make Princes in all Lands; And make them and theirs euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more worthy nurſing fathers and nurſing mothers vnto thy Church. Confirme, O Lord, the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20225:48"/>good things which thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in them, and ſo aſſiſt them with thy grace, that neither Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans ſubtiltie, nor their youthes frailetie, nor the worlds vanitie, nor their peoples flatterie, nor mans wiſdomes policie, may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them from the path of piety. Adorne them more and more with thy graces: cloath them with thy righteouſneſſe, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply vpon them all heroicall and ſpirituall graces, that they may grow vp more and more in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with thee and with men. Bleſſe them whileſt they are here amongſt vs, and bleſſe them when they ſhall bee gone from vs: bleſſe them in their bodies and in their ſoules, in their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and in their Subiects: bleſſe them at home and abroad, by ſea and by land, in peace and in warre: ſmite thorow the loines of thoſe that riſe vp againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: bleſſe thoſe that bleſſe them, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20225:49"/>curſe thoſe that curſe them: keep and protect them as the apple of thine eye; continue their loue, their health, their happines, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long their dayes for many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that they may liue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a long time here in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect loue and amity, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life ended, may feaſt with thee at the Lambes marriage with glory e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetnally: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:20225:49"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
